<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Alex Ptakhin</title>
    <link>https://aptakhin.name/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Alex Ptakhin</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2022 22:00:21 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aptakhin.name/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hiring</title>
      <link>https://aptakhin.name/posts/2022/hiring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2022 22:00:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aptakhin.name/posts/2022/hiring/</guid>
      <description>Hiring is one of the most important problems for a leader. Why is it so difficult? Too many changing surrounding factors. Also, it’s a decision with long-time effects. We can’t definitely predict how new team members will interact with the rest of the team. Especially under changing context.
Let’s make one step back. Can we avoid the requirement of hiring? Can think about it. It’s a significant addition to a small team.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Lot of Work, Reflection and Education</title>
      <link>https://aptakhin.name/posts/2022/a-lot-of-work-reflection-and-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 14:10:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aptakhin.name/posts/2022/a-lot-of-work-reflection-and-education/</guid>
      <description>From my career, I have very subjective experience, but very common from startups and middle-sized to big tech companies. Overloaded everyone from linear managers and above to c-level. Hectic calendars. Many calls and meetings. Often making anything except important and not in-hurry a. And really lack time to think, only to decide.
Even worse, often it&amp;rsquo;s much work because some time ago it was solutions to problems, which were decided to do in the company: how people interact with each other, what is flow from ideas to customer delivery, what are internal steps in the flow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Less-complexity &amp; Fast Feedback Teams</title>
      <link>https://aptakhin.name/posts/2022/less-complexity-and-fast-feedback-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2022 13:07:38 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aptakhin.name/posts/2022/less-complexity-and-fast-feedback-teams/</guid>
      <description>My goal: bring the idea of basic rules about systems. And nudge to think about the decision effects.
Audience: senior engineers, engineering managers, and product/project managers.
There are many overcomplications in the Tech industry regarding how to work well. There are too many “new” concepts, manyP bestseller books, many conferences and many talks with some “new” ideas. We think we missing something we run into it trying to implement things without going deeper into some basis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[ru] Кодревью</title>
      <link>https://aptakhin.name/posts/2020/codereview-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aptakhin.name/posts/2020/codereview-summary/</guid>
      <description>Дисклеймер: ниже заметки субъективных ключевых мест с краткостью записи для себя, оригинал видео рекомендуется к просмотру. Оригинал обсуждения здесь: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IDj3x__YZgE
Зачем код ревью Соответствует ли код требованиям в ТЗ Побочные эффекты. Проблемы в других функциях Читаемость. Странные именования Консистентность общему стилю Оптимальность Чистота Повторное использование существующего кода. Агрессивно DRY Соответствие архитектурного изменения Проверка сценариев тестирования Плюсы:
Уменьшение числа дефектов и увеличение качества кода Совместное владение кодом и бест практик Проблемы Дорого.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[ru] Последний довод зависшего процесса</title>
      <link>https://aptakhin.name/posts/2020/last-in-debugging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aptakhin.name/posts/2020/last-in-debugging/</guid>
      <description>Симптомы. Один из подпроцессов в поде кубернетса просто вис и не логировал данные.
Заходим в поду.
Чтобы понять про процессы:
$ top top - 19:00:06 up 22 days, 10:42, 0 users, load average: 0.79, 0.89, 1.11 Tasks: 13 total, 1 running, 7 sleeping, 0 stopped, 5 zombie %Cpu(s): 1.2 us, 1.4 sy, 0.0 ni, 95.0 id, 2.1 wa, 0.2 hi, 0.1 si, 0.1 st MiB Mem : 32165.3 total, 14305.0 free, 3202.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
