<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <title>Goint to light!</title>
 <id>/</id>
 <updated>2016-01-17T19:25:38.291303Z</updated>
 <author>
   <name>Alexander Ptakhi</name>
 </author>
 <link rel="self" href="/feed.atom"/>
 <link rel="alternate" href="/"/>
 
   <entry>
     <title>Simplification vs Accuracy</title>
     <id>/2014/06/20/simplification-vs-accuracy</id>
     <link rel="alternate" href="/2014/06/20/simplification-vs-accuracy.html"/>
     <updated>2014-06-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
     <content type="xhtml">
       <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
Or why real programmers might hate StackOverflow.com. Problem although more common. There always be argues between simplification and accuracy in describing subject.
As a simple example. We solved at college and university many physics tasks with constant gravity force 9,81 m/s^2. And we omit important words "in homogenous constant force field near Earth ground with relative error 1%".

I think there are no real reason to laugh at programmers who used StackOverflow.

Wikipedia is good enough for first approach. It gives you some base information about unknown subject. The same idea with StackOverflow: you need answers for specific problem, you ask Big Search text field, he asks Google, voila with great chance answer is found. Maybe answer isn't perfect, but remember it's first approach.

It's just like centralized wiki about any language, any library. Does your favourite instrument have good documentation? Really, are you sure that API generated from code is enough?

After writing code with 30% time, we'll debug it 70% of time. And then we can't go rest, we should spend 50%-100% more time to write good documentation.

Caption Obvious often says you should think before using any tool.

Hundreds and thousands programmers deals with hundreds and thousands different problems while programs. It's collection of solutions.

I notice how developers (put me it this list too) find code soluction in network and adopt code for their purposes. Why do we do this? Are we bad programmers? Maybe yes. But surely most of work we do regardless our job is routine work, which doesn't require even enabling of brains. More often job requires out experience in area. Either experiance or you are just very clever guy. Usually we don't sort two-linked arrays with N^2 cost, but while I writing this post Python blog generator will do it many times, but who cares?

What will we do when something [crashes](#allcrashes)? And this is good question.

Without understanding.

Final joke about summation two integers in JavaScript with jQuery.

<ul id="bib">
  <li>[1] <a id="allcrashes" href="https://research.microsoft.com/en-us/people/mickens/thenightwatch.pdf">"The Night Watch" by James mickens</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
     </content>
   </entry>
 
</feed>
